downward facing dog also known as down
dog is a stretching and strengthening
yoga pose found in almost all practices
as either a resting pose a transition or
as a warmup for the entire backline of
your body this foundational yoga pose
will strengthen your wrists and
shoulders while stretching your chest
low back hamstrings and
calves to get into down dog from a
tabletop with your hands directly
underneath your shoulders step your feet
back into a plank with your feet hips
withth distance then lift your hips high
and back as if you were trying to sit on
the wall behind
you gently bend your knees to soften
your lower back and press your chest
towards your thighs to stretch out your
shoulders and lengthen your
spine engage your body as if you were
trying to rip your mat in half between
your hands and feet and you can rest in
place or alternate bending your knees to
warm up your legs and hips be mindful
that you're not cupping your hands on
your mat instead spread your fingers
wide and grip down through your whole
hand even pressing down into the pads of
each of your fingers also please note
that getting your heels to the mat is
not a requirement for alignment
as you gain flexibility and Ankle
Mobility your heels may get closer to
your mat but some space is totally
normal and I'd rather you focus on using
a gentle Bend in your knees to create
more of the triangle shape that will
effectively lengthen the backline of
your body if you're feeling extra tight
in this pose and rounding a lot in your
lower back then try a deeper Bend in
your knees as your body warms up and
becomes more limber you can also modif
this pose with a tabletop instead this
will take the pressure off of your
wrists or it's a good pose to go to if
you feel light headed and you're always
welcome to adjust the width of your
hands and
feet or the length of your stance to
find the position that best serves
you for a deeper stretching and
strengthening variation of down dog try
three- leg down dog by reaching one leg
High into the air you can point your
toes but I recommend that you flex your
foot so that all of your toes face down
towards your mat and you drive back
through your heel this will force your
hips to stay closed to help even out any
imbalances in strength and flexibility
on your right and left
sides hold for three to five deep
breaths then repeat for the same amount
of time on your other side downward
facing dog is a basic yoga pose that you
will experience in most styles of yoga
although it may feel very challenging
when you're new to your practice focus
on the modifications that allow you to
practice optimal alignment without
strain and soon it might feel good and
you may even see why some consider this
a resting pose